<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-hares-idr-common-header-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Common Header">BGP Community Common Header Attribute</title>

    <author fullname="Sue Hares" initials="S." surname="Hares" role="editor">
        <organization>Huawei</organization>
        <address>
            <email>shares@ndzh.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Scudder" initials="J." surname="Scudder" role="editor">
        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
        <address>
            <email>jgs@juniper.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <date month="September" year="2016" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>IDR</workgroup>
    <keyword>BGP</keyword>
    <keyword>communities</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
          The original BGP community attribute as defined by <xref target="RFC1997"/>
          has enjoyed widespread usage. As BGP has evolved, the need for
          several different styles of communities (or "route colors") emerged.
          This document defines a new BGP attribute that can aggregates all new
          styles of communities behind a single BGP Path attribute. The
          community styles contained by this attribute are to be defined in
          separate documents.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
            The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
            "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
            this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>
    </note>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>
            As BGP has evolved, various use cases have presented themselves for
            various flavors of coloring routes. This document defines a new BGP
            attribute that can aggregate all the new styles of route coloring.
            The community styles contained by this attribute are to be defined
            in separate documents.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="BGP Common Community Header Attribute">
        <t>
            This document defines a new BGP Path Attribute, the BGP Common
            Community Header Attribute. The attribute type code is (TBA by
            IANA).
        </t>

        <t>
            The BGP Common Community Header Attribute is an optional,
            transitive BGP attribute. The attribute may be present multiple
            times in a BGP UPDATE message with the unique constraint of the
            tuple (type, global administrator).
        </t>

        <t>
            The attribute is followed by a number of typed communities. Any
            given community type may appear multiple times.
        </t>

       <section title="BGP Community Common Header">

      <t>Communities always start with the following header:
<figure align="center"><artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Type               |          Length               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Global Administrator                    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork></figure></t>
      <t>The fields are as shown below:
      <list style='hanging' hangIndent='10'>
          <t hangText='     Type -'>
              The type of community following the header. The types are to be
              defined in companion documents. This is a two octet field.
          </t>
          <t hangText='     Length -'>
              The number of octets occupied by this header and the communities
              under it. This is a two octet field.
          </t>
          <t hangText='     Global Administrator -'>
              This sub-field contains a 4-octet Autonomous System number
              assigned by IANA.
          </t>
       </list></t>
       <t>
           A BGP speaker that does not recognize a community type SHOULD ignore
           it, but propagate it to other speakers. This behavior MAY be
           overridden by local policy.
       </t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Error Handling">
        <t>
            The BGP Community Common Header attribute MUST have an attribute
            length of at least 8 octets. If this is not the case the UPDATE
            message should be treated as a withdraw.
        </t>
        <t>
            An implementation MUST walk all Common Headers and verify that all
            of the communities fill up the path attribute length. If this is
            not the case, the UPDATE message should be treated as withdrawn.
            Further procedures are described in <xref target="RFC7606"/>.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
        <t>
            Optional transitive transitive BGP attributes could unintentionally
            spread far from their origin. XX insert further deployment.
        </t>
    </section>

<section title="Implementation status - RFC EDITOR: REMOVE BEFORE PUBLICATION">
       <t>
           This section records the status of known implementations of the
           protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of
           this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in
           <xref target="RFC7942" />. The description of implementations in this
           section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in
           progressing drafts to RFCs.  Please note that the listing of any
           individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the
           IETF.  Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the
           information presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors.
           This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog
           of available implementations or their features.  Readers are advised
           to note that other implementations may exist.
       </t>
       <t>
           As of today these vendors have produced an implementation of Large
           BGP Community:
           <list style="symbols">
               <t>ExaBGP</t>
            </list>
       </t>
   </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>
            IANA is requested to assign a BPG path attribute code for the BGP
            Community Common Header Attribute.
        </t>
        <t>
            IANA is requested to create and maintain a registry of community
            types for the Type field.
        </t>
        <t>
            <figure><artwork>
Name                       Type Value      Transitivity
----                       ----------      ------------
Reserved                   0x0000          n/a
IETF Consensus             0x0001-0x02AA   Transitive
IETF Consensus             0x02AB-0x0555   Non-Transitive
First come First served    0x0556-0x07FF   Transitive
First come First served    0x0800-0x0AAA   Non-Transitive
Experimental use           0x0AAB-0x0FFF   Non-Transitive
Reserved                   0x1000-0xFFFF   n/a
</artwork></figure>
        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>
            This document represents a long journey in which many people were
            instrumental in resolving various prisoner dilemmas. 
        </t>
        <t>
            Robert Raszuk, Jeff Haas, Jakob Heitz, Keyur Patel, Jared Mauch,
            Andrew Lange, Shane Amante, Bruno Decraene, Paul Jakma, Richard A.
            Steenbergen, Shintaro Kojima, Juan Alcaide, Burjiz Pithawala, Saku
            Ytti, Igor Gashinsky and Job Snijders.
        </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1997"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7606"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7942"?>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
